first thing that the person should clear
which appear with themselves is why why
do they want to meditate
and of course I'm assuming we're talking
about Buddhist meditation not many other
poems the person could be doing for all
sorts of reasons so from a point of view
of the Buddhist meditation uniform are
they want to medical are you just
seeking out new experiences are you just
seeking out to the place experiences
there used to with some new experience
is something that's the mobility or are
you doing a meditation just to
strengthen your mind so it's it's quite
obvious which one you will see there is
no meditation without virtue being
developed beforehand so a person needs
to be virtuous which means the person is
to be able to exercise a degree of
self-control which means that meditation
then becomes exactly about developing of
that same strength being able to say no
to yourself and then being able to not
be pulled by the by the censors and
fleeting desires in regard to that so so
that's why it's important to to clarify
and also keep the manuals of why you are
meditating in the first place but
sometimes you can get pulled by various
love the experiences that comes to just
come sitting and being mindful of your
breath and so on but all of those things
are completely secondary you are not
after after the pursuit of pleasure in
regard to them after the procedures of
novelty experiences you really is after
development of strength clarity of
mindfulness and ultimately understanding
that's why we would say that if someone
is fully developed it will bring the
to fulfilment and wisdom is certainly
enough to rise on account of chasing the
content of your experience wisdom can
only arise on account of understanding
the nature of that experience which
basically transcends the content so
that's why it doesn't really matter what
type of experiences a person has during
their meditation the body feels light
heavy or like this or like that
what matters is their mindfulness of it
and whether whether that mindfulness is
affected and how developed it is and the
clarity clarity of understanding in
regard to any of those experiences
because whether the body feels light or
heavy whether feels impersonal or personal the
whether feels impersonal or personal the
body is there and that's where the
mindfulness should be pertaining to and
that's something that's developed and
strengthened through through the
meditation so regardless of the
meditation technique and so on whatever
person might be doing the point is to
stop being absorbed with the content and
start looking at the nature that's where
the Dharma means nature nature of things
unless unless a person starts
intentionally looking and trying to
discern the nature of a reason things
you can't develop understanding of it it
can't happen by itself to some magical
method or something only you can develop
understanding of the nature of things if
you keep trying to understand the nature
of things so so by all means people
should meditate people should set set
set some time aside during the day to
sit sit quietly
in an undisturbed environment but they
should use their time to develop
mindfulness in regard to their situation
in regard to the nature of their
experience the nature of feeling the
nature of attention to nature of action
no the ways of practicing that
concentration because samadhi the
practice of samadhi literally means
keeping things together Samadhi means
keeping things together and so so rather
than thinking about practicing rather
than thinking about them concentration
when it comes to Samadhi in meditation a
person should think about them of
mindfulness and composure really keeping
things together means composing things
and maintaining that composition so to
speak and that composition must be
founded upon mindfulness as the Buddha
would would have explained it we don't
mention any many of the suitors and the
mindfulness must not be compromised so
that's how that's like a basic rule of
thumb how to meditate
maintain the clarity of your intention
in regard to the reasons for meditation
and and don't use it as an escape don't
use it as a replacement don't use it to
seek our pleasure use it to develop
self-control use that time of meditation
to develop mindfulness and to understand
the standard nature things understand
how you've been fooled by that are you
being pulled by the feelings how they
control you understand how you can
become careless in regard to your
wholesome and unwholesome intentions so
so there's a wide range of things a
person can be countably be right in the
meditation